Guide to the James Crumley Papers
The Wittliff Collections
James Crumley Papers
1965-1992, undated
The Wittliff Collections
Crumley, James, 1939-2008
SWWC.055
5 Linear Feet
9 boxes Includes oversize and artifacts.
Nine boxes of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs, poetry, screenplays, short stories and artifacts, 1957-1992, document the writing career of James Crumley.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Crumley, 1992.
Biographical Notes
Novelist James Crumley was born in Three Rivers, Texas, on October 12, 1939 and spent most of his childhood in south Texas. He maintained a straight-A average in high school while also playing football. After graduation he attended the Georgia Institute of Technology in Atlanta on a Navy ROTC scholarship, but soon left to enlist in the U.S. Army, where he served from 1958 to 1961. Crumley then returned to Texas and enrolled at Texas A&I (now Texas A&M University-Kingsville), where he had received a football scholarship. Crumley completed his BA in History in 1964, and was accepted into the University of Iowa's prestigious creative writing program, where he earned a MFA in 1966. Immediately after graduating he joined the English faculty at the University of Montana at Missoula. His masters thesis was eventually published as the novel, "One to Count Cadence, in 1969, a popular and critically acclaimed look at the Vietnam War. After his novel was published, Crumley left Montana to hold a series of visiting professorships: the University of Arkansas at Fayetteville (1969-70), Colorado State University (1971-74), Reed College in Portland, Oregon (1976-1977), Carnegie-Mellon University (1979-1980) and the University of Texas at El Paso (1981-1984.)
During a two-year stretch as a freelance writer (1974-1976) Crumley published the first in a series of crime novels for which he would become known. The Wrong Case (1975) featured a detective named Milo Milodragovitch, who would also appear in later novels. "I always introduce my work by explaining that I am a bastard child of Raymond Chandler – without his books, my books would be completely different. We cover some of the same ground, his dark streets in LA, my twisted highways in the mountain west. But because of the events surrounding the Vietnam War, my detectives are not as comfortable with traditional morality as Philip Marlowe seems to be," (Contemporary Authors, 2000).
In 1978 The Last Good Kiss (1978) was published, which introduced Crumley's other detective protagonist, C.W. Sughrue. His third crime novel, Dancing Bear (Milodragovitch series), was published in 1983. After leaving his last teaching job in 1984, Crumley has worked full-time as a writer. He's made his home base in Missoula, Montana since the mid-1980s. He has worked on film screenplays, which remain unproduced, and has continued to write and publish fiction. The Muddy Fork and Other Things: Short Fiction and Nonfiction was published in 1991, featuring many of Crumley's short stories. The detective series continued with The Mexican Tree Duck (Sughrue series) in 1993, and Bordersnakes (1996), which brought together Milodragovitch and Sughrue for the first time.
According to Robert E. Burkholder in the Dictionary of Literary Biography Yearbook (1984), Crumley's crime novels stand "the genre on its head by creating an antiheroic protagonist plagued by the weakness and vice of the corrupt world in which he lives and works and endowing him, nevertheless, with the sort of noble instincts that motivate him to sift through the scum in order to identify right from wrong. Crumley's detectives are curiously amoral moralists."
Crumley's final published works include The Putt at the End of the World (2000); the Milodragovitch series novel, The Final Country (2001); and one in the Sughrue series, The Right Madness (2005). He passed away September 17, 2008 from complications from kidney and pulmonary disease.
Scope and Contents
Nine boxes of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs, poetry, screenplays, short stories and artifacts, 1957-1992, document the writing career of James Crumley. The collection has been arranged into five series: Works, 1965-1992; Correspondence, 1957-1986; Clippings 1971-1992; Personal Materials, 1957-1979; and Works by Others, undated.
The Works series comprises the largest part of the collection. It documents Crumley's writing process from drafts through proof copy or published work. The Novels subseries makes up the largest portion of the series, with the numerous Dancing Bear files documenting Crumley's changing ideas for titles and other aspects related to the novel. The Correspondence series contains mostly fan letters written to him, but also includes correspondence regarding the film rights for Crumley's novel, One to Count Cadence. The Personal series contains photographs, certificates and legal documents related to Crumley's education, military career, and marriages. Works by Others include screenplays based on Crumley's novel The Last Good Kiss, and poetry.
Detective and mystery stories; Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Screenplays; Poems; Crumley, James, 1939-2008
- Novels, 1965-1992
  Scope and Contents
  This series has been arranged in chronological order by date of the novel's creation. This is the largest series, with the numerous Dancing Bear files documenting Crumley's changing ideas for titles and other aspects related to the novel. Although multiple drafts of each work are present, the drafts typically include only the first few chapters of the work. The specific portions of each work represented and any variant titles are identified by the folder titles. Each of Crumley's novels is represented here, including one unpublished novel, by the title "Meat."
  - One to Count Cadence, 1965-1971
    - Second draft, October 1965 - April 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Excerpts and Editor's note, March 15, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Typesetting copy (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Author's 1st proof galley, December 26, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Author's 2nd proof galley (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Clippings, 1969, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Wrong Case, 1975
    - Typescript photocopy (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, February 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Reviews, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Last Good Kiss, 1978-1984
    - Annotated Typescript, circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Book jacket (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Reviews, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Movie contract with Warner Brothers Inc., January 6, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dancing Bear (Annotated typescript fragments with various titles), 1983, undated
    - Typescript (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Annotated typescript - "Walking Backwards" (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Annotated typescript - "Milo version," Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Milo version," Chapter 1, second draft (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Milo version," Chapters 1-5, first draft (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "The Muddy Fork," Milo version (original and photocopy) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "A Plague of Orphans," Chapter 1 fragments (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "TRW" (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - "The Local Memory" Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - "Soledad City" Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - "Drunk on the Wind" Chapter 1, pages 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Drunk on the Wind" Chapter 1, pages 1-9 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "Drunk on the Wind" Chapters 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "The Dead Heart" Chapters 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "Drawing Blood" Chapter 1, pages 4-5 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Drawing Blood" Chapter 1, pages 1-9 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "Drawing Blood" Chapter 1, pages 1-22 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "Drawing Blood" Chapter 1, pages 28-38 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "Drawing Blood" Chapter 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - "Without Drawing Blood" Chapter 1, pages 4-12 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - "Without Drawing Blood" Chapter 1 fragments (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Without Drawing Blood/ Mahagen" Chapter 1, first draft (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - "Without Drawing Blood/ Mahagen" Chapter 1, second draft (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Snow" Chapter 1, pages 2-6 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "It's Snowing in the Foothills of My Heart" Title page with no typescript (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Reviews, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 28, Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Title page of screenplay (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mexican Tree Duck (Annotated typescripts by various titles), circa 1992
    - "A Wild Justice" Chapter 1, pages 1-5, circa 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "MD" Chapter 1, pages 1-5, circa 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Mexican Tree Duck" Chapter 1, pages 1-2, circa 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Mexican Tree Duck" Chapter 1, pages 1-10, circa 1992 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Meat, unpublished (Annotated typescripts by various titles), undated
    - "CT" Chapters 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "UT" Chapter 1, pages 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "UT" Chapters 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "Meat" Chapter 1, pages 1-3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Meat" Chapter 1, pages 1-14 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - "Meat" Chapter 1, pages 1-20 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - "Meat" Chapter 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "Meat" carbon typescript, pages 1-98 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - "Meat" carbon typescript, pages 1-112 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Short Stories, 1971-1981
  This series has been arranged in alphabetical order by title, and includes mainly annotated typescripts and fragments of each short story, as well as one galley, and one carbon copy.
  - "Another Poet in Montana" typescript, pages 1-10, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Cairn" annotated typescript, circa 1978 (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - "Cousin" first draft, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Daddy's Gone a-Hunting" second draft, circa 1974 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Dirty Works" pages 1-7, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "Driving Around Houston" pages 1-27a, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - "The Fastest Man in Nebraska" first draft, August 10, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - "Goodbye Cruel World" first draft, December 21-27, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Goodbye Cruel World" second draft, December 28, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - "Goodbye Cruel World" typescript, January 4, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - "Goodbye Cruel World" carbon typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - "The Heavy" typescript (original and photocopy), undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - "The Heavy" galley copy, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - "An Ideal Son for the Jenkins Family" annotated typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - "Labor Pains" annotated typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - "Moons," annotated typescript, page 2 only, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - "The Philanderer" first draft, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Philanderer" annotated typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "The Philanderer" annotated typescript, original and photocopy, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "Roadsigns, Roadcircles, and Detours" annotated typescript and published version, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - "Story" page 1, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Story" pages 1-2, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Story" pages 1-5, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "Story" pages 1-7, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "The Sunbathers", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "Things I Can't Write About and the Reasons Why", undated (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
  - "Three Cheers for Thomas J. Rabb" pages 1-20, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "Three Cheers for Thomas J. Rabb" pages 1-32, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "Three Forks" pages 1-6, undated (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - "Three Forks" page 4, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Untitled (Military Air Transportation), undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Whores", circa 1977 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Screenplays, 1978-1990
  Arranged in alphabetical order by title of screenplay, this series includes typescripts of screenplays based on Crumley's novels Dancing Bear and The Last Good Kiss, as well others not based on Crumley's novels.
  - "Ain't No God in Mexico" annotated typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - "The Big Nowhere" first draft, November 16, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - "Dancing Bear" Revised typescript (with Tim Hunter), undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - "Judge Dredd," revised first draft (with Tim Hunter), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - "The Last Good Kiss" first draft, January 21, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "The Pigeon Shoot" movie synopsis (English July 20, 1983 and Spanish August 5, 1983) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "The Pigeon Shoot" first draft, December 13, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "The Pigeon Shoot" first draft (photocopy), December 13, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "The Sheepeater Campaign" notes, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "The Sheepeater Campaign" typescript, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - "Tunnels of Cu Chi" second draft (with Tim Hunter), undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - "Untitled" first draft (with Gwenyth Mapes), August 1988 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Poetry, undated
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title and includes two annotated typescripts of poems apparently written by Crumley.
  - Food for the Dogs, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - How to Survive Your Life, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1957-1986
  Arranged in order from earliest to most recent, the correspondence in this series consists largely of fan letters written to Crumley, as well as two 1957 letters from Senator Lyndon Baines Johnson congratulating Crumley on his scholastic achievements. Several drafts of letters written by Crumley are also included, such as a 1969 letter to MGM studios regarding a film treatment of One to Count Cadence.
  - 1957-1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1978-1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1971-1992
  This series includes newspaper and magazine articles related to Crumley's literary career.
  - Clippings and articles on or about Crumley, 1971-1992 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Personal, 1957-1979
  This series contains photographs, certificates and legal documents related to Crumley's education, military career, and marriages, as well as a steel hardhat and cap.
  - US Army Football photographs and team roster, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - US Navy certificates of accomplishment, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - College transcripts (University of Iowa, MFA English, 1970, Texas College of Arts and Sciences, BA, 1965), 1965, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Wedding photograph, bride Sandra L. McCollough, Refugio, TX, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Divorce decrees, Sandra L. Crumley (1968), Margaret L. Crumley (1975), Judith Ann Ramey (1979), 1968, 1975, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Vitae, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Blue and white baseball cap from Montana Review of Books, and a steel hardhat with initials JAC scratched on inside brim (Box 9)
- Works by Others, undated
  Subseries A: Screenplays (undated) Arranged in alphabetical order by author, this subseries includes two screenplays based on Crumley's novel The Last Good Kiss.
  Subseries B: Poetry (undated) Also arranged in alphabetical order by author, this subseries includes poetry by Kathy Callaway (1 folder), various authors (1 folder), and unidentified authors (1 folder).
  - Screenplays, undated
    - "The Last Good Kiss" revised screenplay by Walter Hill, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "The Last Good Kiss," First Draft by Michael Jenning, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Poetry, undated
    - Poems by Kathy Callaway, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Poems by various authors, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - No authors, undated (Box 8, Folder 14)